Finding Aid for Marcus Llewellyn Ward Papers 1906-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Marcus Llewellyn Ward Papers
1906-1962
Ward, Marcus Llewellyn, 1875-1963.
Professor of dentistry and dean of the School of Dentistry at University of Michigan. Personal files primarily concerning his professional interests and activities; and university files detailing his relationship with various officials.
86207 Aa 2
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was received in several accession from Dr. and Mrs. Ward (donor no. 3472 )
The collection is open for research.
Marcus Llewellyn Ward was born on August 5, 1875 in Howell, Michigan. He attended the University of Michigan and received from that institution the degrees of D.D.S. (1902) and D.D.Sc, (1905).
While most dentists preferred private practice, Ward's interest lay in the areas of teaching and research. He spent his entire life doing both as a member of the University of Michigan's School of Dentistry faculty. In 1903 he was named instructor of operative technics and operative dentistry. In 1905 he was named lecturer and in 1908 was made a professor. In 1912 the Dental School formally recognized Ward's changing interests when his title was changed from Professor of Operative Principles to Professor of Dental Physics and Chemistry. This change of title acknowledged Ward's pioneering research into the nature of dental cements and filling materials.
In 1919 Ward the Regents appointed Ward dean of the Dental School. He served in that position until 1934, when he resigned from the deanship but continued as a professor within the school. Between 1934 and 1945, when he retired from teaching altogether, Ward's held the title of Jonathan Taft Professor of Dentistry.
Ward's concern for dentistry carried him beyond the campus to become a key national figure within the profession. He was deeply involved with the Michigan State Dental Association, helping to revive the organization in the first decade of the twentieth century and serving as its president in 1912. He was involved with the American Association of Dental Schools, serving as that group's president in 1925. Ward was also active in the American Dental Association, once again serving in a variety of positions, including president (1939). After his retirement from teaching, Ward remained very active in professional dental organizations. He was particularly concerned about the history of the Michigan State Dental Association, helping organize that group's centennial celebration and subsequently arranging for the writing of a book length history.
Marcus Ward died in 1963.
The Ward papers measure four linear feet and date from 1906 to 1962. They have been divided into two series; the Personal and University Records. Both series are arranged alphabetically. The collections relates almost exclusively to his professional career and interests.
Subjects:
Dentistry--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dentists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Dental Association.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Dentistry.; Ward, Marcus Llewellyn, 1875-1963.
- Personal, 1906-1962
  The Personal series contains information on a broad range of subjects, but generally lacks depth on any particular topic. Because Ward almost always filed correspondence by the last name of the individual it was addressed to, rather than by the institutional affiliation of the person, material about the same organization is often widely scattered. Most interesting are Ward's research files (on "Dental Cements", "Dental Fillings" and "Laboratory Laws and Technicians") and Ward's information on the Michigan State Dental Association. Most of Ward's post 1945 material relates to the history of the MSDA.
  - Adams, Philip E., 1952-1961 (Box 1)
  - Aging, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1935 (Box 1)
  - American College of Dentists, 1957-1962 (Box 1)
  - American, Dental Association, 1924-1958; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - American Medical Association, Health Insurance, 1935 (Box 1)
  - American Textbook of Operative Dentistry, 1936-1942; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Angell, James R., National Broadcasting Company, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Applegate, Stere G., University of Detroit School of Dentistry, 1945-1953 (Box 1)
  - Army Medical Library, 1944-1952 (Box 1)
  - Asbell, Milton S., 1958 (Box 1)
  - Atlanta-Southern Dental College, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Baltimore College of Dental Surgery, 1921 (Box 1)
  - Blackerby, Philip E., W.K. Kellogg Foundation, 1946-1952 (Box 1)
  - Brucker, Wilbur M., 1947-1951 (Box 1)
  - C General, 1929-1933 (Box 1)
  - Camalier, C. Willard, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Capillarity, circa 1939 (Box 1)
  - Certification/Certificate Design, circa 1935-1938 (Box 1)
  - Champagne, J.L., Michigan State Board of Dentistry, 1947-1960 (Box 1)
  - Cheney, Eduard A., 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - Children's Dentistry, 1939-1942 (Box 1)
  - Children's Fund of Michigan, 1929-1935 (Box 1)
  - Cleveland Dental Manufacturing Company, 1941-1944 (Box 1)
  - Clopper, Paul W., 1956-1961 (Box 1)
  - Coffey, Ralph, North Carolina Dental Society, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Conway, Bernard J., American Dental Association, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Cook, William A., 1957-1961 (Box 1)
  - Crane, Kenneth F., Wisconsin State Dental Society, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Bill, University of Minnesota School of Dentistry, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum, 1930-1934 (Box 1)
  - de Castro, H., 1958 (Box 1)
  - Definitions, Nomenclature and Terminology, 1935-1953; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Delta Sigma Delta, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Demonstrations of Technique, circa 1935 (Box 1)
  - Dental Assistants, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Dental Cements, 1915-1917 (Box 1)
  - Dental Fillings, 1906-1930 (Box 1)
  - Dental Laws, 1937-1943 (Box 1)
  - Dental Manpower Survey, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Dental School Survey, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Denton, George B., 1956 (Box 1)
  - Distinction Press, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Donnelly, Andrew J., 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Dow, Thomas D., 1955 (Box 1)
  - Easlick Lectures (Box 1)
  - Eaton, Earl M., 1949 (Box 1)
  - Erickson, K.C., 1948 (Box 1)
  - Ernst, Max E., 1951 (Box 1)
  - Ethics and Dental Laws, 1953-1961; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Faggart, Harold L., American Academy for the History of Dentistry, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Ferris Institute, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Flouride, 1948-1959 (Box 2)
  - Friedrick, Rudolph H., American Dental Association, 1956-1959 (Box 2)
  - Fuller, B.F., 1952 (Box 2)
  - Fusilier, O.J., Michigan State Dental Association Centennial Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - Gabel, Arthur B., School of Dentistry, University of Pennsylvania, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Gerendasy, Samuel, Congress of American Dentists, 1957-1961 (Box 2)
  - Gibson, Kenneth, 1942-1949 (Box 2)
  - Gies, William J., 1935-1951 (Box 2)
  - Goulding, Peter C., American Dental Association, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Graduate and Post-Graduate Work, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Green, Henry, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Greetings/Vita of Ward (Box 2)
  - Grob, Albert H., Michigan State Dental Association Centennial Publicity Committee, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Gullett, Don W., Canadian Dental Association, 1946-1950 (Box 2)
  - H General, 1948-1953 (Box 2)
  - Harper, Charles F., New Jersey State Dental Society, 1941-1947 (Box 2)
  - Harris, George S., Michigan State Dental Association Centennial Publicity Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - Harvard Dental School Curriculum, 1939 (Box 2)
  - Herbine, Frederick W., American Dental Association, 1949-1951 (Box 2)
  - Hillenbrand, Harold, American Dental Association, 1947-1961 (Box 2)
  - History of the Dental School, 1875-1921 (Box 2)
    Excerpts from Regents Minutes
  - Horner, Harlan H., 1950 (Box 2)
  - Hunt, Josephine P., American Dental Association, 1940 (Box 2)
  - International Association for Dental Research, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Jarvie Fellowship, 1939-1944 (Box 2)
  - Jesserich, Paul H., 1950 (Box 2)
  - Jesson, Stanley, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Kittell, H.G., New York State Board of Dental Examiners, 1948-1950 (Box 2)
  - Laboratory Laws and Technicians, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Lectures and Lecture Material, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Leitch, Murray A., Michigan State Dental Association, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - Library, 1935-1943 (Box 2)
  - Licensing (Box 2)
  - Lyons, Harry, 1943-1957 (Box 2)
  - Macomb County Dental Society, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Marshall, Duncan, Atlas Dental Company, 1946-1948 (Box 2)
  - McCluggage, Robert W., 1956 (Box 2)
  - McNulty, Robert W., American Association of Dental Schools, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Medical School Admission, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Merritt, Arthur H., 1940-1944 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Dental Laboratories, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Department of Health, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Dental Association, 1908-1961; 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1908-1911; 1937; 1961 (Box 3)
  - Moen, Obed H., American Dental Association, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
  - Morrey, Lon W., American Dental Association, 1947-1961 (Box 3)
  - Morris, Emory Wi, Kellogg Foundation, 1937-1945 (Box 3)
  - New York Academy of Dentistry, 1935-1945 (Box 3)
  - New York State Board of Dental Examiners, 1916-1932 (Box 3)
  - Patton, Charles H., 1958 (Box 3)
  - Pedodontics, Organization of a National Society, circa 1942 (Box 3)
  - Peyton, Floyd A., 1942 (Box 3)
  - Philips, Percy, 1947-1962 (Box 3)
  - Pollock, H.C., Orthodontics at Michigan, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Prince, M. Webster, 1949-1952 (Box 3)
  - Problems in Teaching by Frederick C. Waite, undated (Box 3)
  - Prosthetic Dental Service, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Publications (Box 3)
  - Reed, E., Dental Laboratories Institute of America, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - Roberts Rules of Order (Box 3)
  - Robinson, J. Ben, Baltimore College of Dental Surgery, 1934-1954; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Ryan, Kenneth J., 1956-1959 (Box 3)
  - Sallade, George W., State Representative, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Sawicki, Alphonse C., 1959 (Box 3)
  - Sayles, Robert D., 1958 (Box 3)
  - Schwartz, L. Laszlo, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Seligson, David, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Shearon Medical Legislative Service, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Shehan, H.L., 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - Short, J. Robert, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Shulman, Albert B., 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Snow, H. Leon, Michigan State Dental Association, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Stoler, Wayne K., 1955-1956 (Box 3)
  - Sweetnam, W.H., 1960 (Box 3)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association, 1943 (Box 3)
  - Technician's Society, 1946-1948 (Box 3)
  - Trustees, Michigan State Dental Association, 1956-1958 (Box 3)
  - University Club, 1938-1940; 1960 (Box 3)
  - Vita (Box 3)
    (see "Greetings/Vita of Ward")
  - Vorys, Harry, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Walker, Bernard H., 1955 (Box 3)
  - Walmoth, R.W., 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Warner, Robert, Research Notes, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Washburn, Donald, American Dental Association, 1952-1955 (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw District Dental Society, 1956-1962 (Box 3)
  - Watling, John, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Weinberger, Bernhard Wolf, 1942-1945 (Box 3)
  - Wertheimer, Fred, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Wilkinson, Maude A., 1960 (Box 3)
  - Winchell, P.M., 1962 (Box 3)
  - Wisan, Jack M., 1946 (Box 3)
  - Wylie, Wendall L., 1946 (Box 3)
  - Zazzaro, Michael J., 1960 (Box 3)
- University Records, 1917-1935
  The University Records series is largely composed of Ward's correspondence while dean with various university officials, primarily the president (Marion L. Burton, Harry B. Hutchins, Clarence C. Cook, and Alexander Ruthven), vice president in charge of business (Shirley Smith), the register (Ira Smith) and the dean of the Graduate School (Alfred H. Lloyd). This series helps fill a gap in the records of the University of Michigan's School of Dentistry.
  - Administrative Information Sheets, 1933-1934 (Box 3)
  - Burton, Marion L., 1920-1924; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Committee on Entrance-Requirements, 1929-1934 (Box 3)
  - Hutchins, Harry B., 1918-1920 (Box 4)
  - Little, Clarence Cook, 1925-1929; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Lloyd, Alfred H., 1919-1927 (Box 4)
  - Ruthven, Alexander G., 1929-1932; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Smith, Ira M., 1925-1930; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Smith, Shirley W., 1918-1927; 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Ward, Marcus L., 1917-1935; 4 folders (Box 4)